<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Hassen Harzallah</title><link>https://hhassen.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on Hassen Harzallah</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 10:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hhassen.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>My Bitcoins almost disappeared forever: Fixing a Crashing Blockstream Green Lightning Wallet</title><link>https://hhassen.github.io/posts/2025/09/my-bitcoins-almost-disappeared-forever-fixing-a-crashing-blockstream-green-lightning-wallet/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hhassen.github.io/posts/2025/09/my-bitcoins-almost-disappeared-forever-fixing-a-crashing-blockstream-green-lightning-wallet/</guid><description>I recently faced every Bitcoiner’s nightmare: I had just bought my first Bitcoin, set up Blockstream Green with a Lightning account, and suddenly the app on my Android phone started crashing immediately at startup. My Lightning funds were locked inside my phone, and unlike with on-chain Bitcoin, writing down my seed phrase wasn’t enough — Lightning state lives on-device.
I contacted Blockstream support right away. Unfortunately, the process was long, and their answers didn’t solve anything:</description></item><item><title>Monitoring to detect incidents</title><link>https://hhassen.github.io/posts/2021/12/monitoring-to-detect-incidents/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Dec 2021 10:10:23 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hhassen.github.io/posts/2021/12/monitoring-to-detect-incidents/</guid><description>Recently, I have worked with a team developing a Spring Boot application. The application is deployed as a Java container in AWS and the logs are stored in Cloudwatch. The application was put behind an Nginx reverse proxy and Nginx logs are also stored in Cloudwatch. Every thing was going fine until they started adding new features that caused very high response times on the prod. Problems become more and more recurrent, developers were exhausted dealing with all this headache and users were very unsatisfied.</description></item><item><title>Kubernetes project: deploy a Sentiment Analysis application</title><link>https://hhassen.github.io/posts/2020/06/kubernetes-project-deploy-a-sentiment-analysis-application/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2020 07:17:23 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hhassen.github.io/posts/2020/06/kubernetes-project-deploy-a-sentiment-analysis-application/</guid><description>In this project, I have deployed a Sentiment Analysis application using Kubernetes on the cloud (Amazon EKS).
The application is composed of 3 main components:
Frontend App : uses React and Nginx to provide user interface Web App : developed with Java to communicate with backend Backend App : Logic part develeped with Python Please find more information in my repo.
Credits to Rinor Maloku for the code and the original article.</description></item><item><title>About Me</title><link>https://hhassen.github.io/about/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Jun 2020 19:22:13 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hhassen.github.io/about/</guid><description>Hi, my name is Hassen Harzallah. I&amp;rsquo;m passionate about computers and new technology.
I&amp;rsquo;m also AWS Solutions Architect Associate certified.
M.Sc. Engineering &amp;lsquo;19 @ ENSTA Paris + @ ENIT
import skills Containerized environments = [ Kubernetes, Docker] AWS Cloud Linux = [ Debian, CentOS, Ubuntu] Automation &amp;amp; IaaC = [ Ansible, Terraform, CloudFormation] Progamming = [ Python, Javascript, C, C++ ] Machine Learning = [ Sklearn, Keras, Tensorflow] Monitoring &amp;amp; Logging = [ Elasticseach, Logstash, Kibana, Grafana] Security = [ Forensics, Reverse Engineering, Cryptography] import Misc Design = [ Adobe Photoshop, Adobe Premiere, 3Ds Max, V-ray] ❤️ Kubernetes, Cloud, Linux, OSS</description></item><item><title>Transférer vos appels sur Skype</title><link>https://hhassen.github.io/posts/2019/07/transf%C3%A9rer-vos-appels-sur-skype/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2019 20:11:23 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hhassen.github.io/posts/2019/07/transf%C3%A9rer-vos-appels-sur-skype/</guid><description>Procédure pour recevoir vos appels téléphoniques en dehors de l&amp;rsquo;union européen (ex: Tunisie), en utilisant un numéro français Skype.
Remarque: cette méthode ne vous permet que de recevoir les appels, elle ne vous permet pas d&amp;rsquo;appeler vers la France.
Procédure: Acheter un numéro français Skype ( environ 8€/mois) https://www.skype.com/fr/features/online-number/ Le numéro a le format français suivant : +33 09 xx xx xx. Lorsque quelqu&amp;rsquo;un appelle ce numéro, vous recevez un appel Skype normal (appel non téléphonique).</description></item><item><title>Initial Commit</title><link>https://hhassen.github.io/posts/2019/07/initial-commit/</link><pubDate>Sat, 13 Jul 2019 22:17:23 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hhassen.github.io/posts/2019/07/initial-commit/</guid><description>Hello World!</description></item></channel></rss>